Software Engineering Radio episode 24,
development processes part one.
Hi everybody.
This episode has Arno and um Alex on the
microphones and we're going to speak
about development processes.
There were actually quite a lot of
listeners
giving us the feedback that they would
like to hear about development processes
and so we at last got down to actually
talking about this and having this topic
in an episode.
So,
Alex,
what will we actually be covering in
this episode?
Uh first of all, we will talk about why
we need development processes, what are
they for. Um later on we will
get a bit theory, process theory, the
very basics, what process types are
there. Um and the foundations to to
speak about process theory. We will not
talk about actual development process in
this episode. We will save this for
later episodes because every development
process I can think of
for example, extreme programming or
Rational Unified Process is so huge
that we can easily fill a whole episode
with it. Um so we leave this out today
and speak only about the very basics.
So, this is sort of the introductory
episode to development processes and
then we will cover different aspects,
different concrete processes and yeah,
different things in later episodes, go
into more detail and probably
yeah, react to feedback we get anyway,
but look at the mainstream processes.
Exactly.
So, let's start by looking at what
actually is a development process. What
is it composed of? And what are the key
aspects?
Well, very simple development process
actually says how a team of software
developers or
other roles together build software. So,
it's it's about teams, how they work
together
for building software.
Therefore, software development process
usually defines roles that says what
people can do or what they have to do
and artifacts, the things they produce
and of course the process steps
which define what will be done at what
what
point in time in the development. So,
it's about working together and doing
software development together.
Well, but playing devil's advocate, I
mean, me and my friends get down, we sit
down together, have this great idea for
a new software product, make it open
source, we get together and just start
coding. What do we need a process for?
Why don't you just dig into things? I
mean
Yeah. Um at first of
create creating all these artifacts and
that sort of thing sounds like overhead.
Why do we need it?
Yeah. Uh well, first of all, maybe um
it's it's a bit a kind of well,
people argue about if every
development team has a process or not or
if you have to have a defined process, a
written down process to have a process.
So,
I don't want to argue if it's a process
just when it's uh written down. But the
important thing is when a team works
together, you have to define how you
work together.
And the problem is or becomes much
harder the the larger the team
gets actually. I mean, if your example,
when two developers work together, uh
you don't have to write down when you
have to do what, of course, because you
just
talk about it and then do it. So,
um it it's gets more complicated the
larger the team size gets, actually.
And so So, so actually development
processes are more important the larger
the teams get. But are they important
for small teams as well?
Um they are important for small teams,
too, in my opinion, at least. Um but
they they get more important for larger
teams. I mean, for smaller teams, you
also have the communication problems and
or you can have communication problems.
Um you have maybe problems who has to do
what and when. So, you you define it
either way. I mean, you don't have to
use extreme programming or Rational
Unified Process for this thing, but you
usually uh talk together and then
define, "Okay, I do the testing. I check
out when you have done this and that."
So, um you usually define processes even
if you don't come or write them down as
formal formal things. Another important
aspect on this thing is for me um
Good development process are also well
kind of best practices. You can uh look
at extreme programming, for example, the
whole unit testing and test-driven
development thing. That are best
practices developer have created over
the years. So, a development process,
even for small teams, can introduce best
practices to your team. So, yes, it's
important for a small team, too, in my
opinion.
So, this sounds like the culture that is
there
can be formalized into a process.
And in a healthy project, the culture
and the process are sort of the same
thing.
And people just wrote down the way
things are done, the way things have
proven to work well, and that in the end
was the process.
Very nice definition, yeah. Very nice
definition, actually, yeah.
Okay, well,
looking at processes this way,
they um mean, it's sort of obvious that
it's good to have them or well, at least
we think they're helpful. But what do
you think? Why are there so many
developers who do not like processes,
for whom for development process is sort
of like a red flag, something they try
to avoid, they try to work around, that
sort of thing?
Yeah, um
uh for me, the main problem is that
actually a lot of
projects use the wrong process, the
wrong process for the project. Um
which has many roots, of course. Uh one
of the the well, common faults is that a
external department, a process um
department, special process department
defines how to program, how processes
should like, and um they they usually
don't know exactly how developers work
or how it's best for them to work. And
um also, they define one process for all
the projects you have in your your
company, and of course, the projects are
different. So, um
often the process don't fit very very
well. Another thing is
But but but but isn't that sort of an
automatic thing that happens? I mean,
processes are sort of um out of the box,
you get them shrink-wrapped.
And um
I mean, if you start a software project,
you usually do not have the time to
think up your own new process. So, what
would be the alternative?
Um
there are there are different ways to
approach this, actually. And um
in my opinion, this is this is one of
the huge breakthroughs we have done in
the last, well, 5 to 10 years in in
process world. I mean,
much earlier, you you really did this it
this way. You had one process, and you
had to fit your project to the process,
which of course, didn't work.
Um
right now, we have the the we we know
that this doesn't work. So, the
different solution for this are
um for example, um extreme programming
defines very strictly where it fits. So,
you can judge you can you look at your
project
judge afterwards is extreme programming
the right process for me.
Another way is how the Rational Unified
Process does it. It's like a toolbox. I
mean,
no one you really uses or you shouldn't
use Rational Unified Process with all
the things that come with it.
Every time you do a project project with
Rational Unified Process, you have to
pick out the the tools out of the
toolbox
you you that fits to your project. So,
you have to customize the project. And
the process.
preach that. Preach that. I mean, yeah.
These sort of process frameworks need to
be tailored for each project, but
especially for Rational Unified Process,
it's it's hardly ever done in my
experience. Or many many companies say,
"Oh, well, great. Rational Unified
Process defines 247 artifacts, I think.
So, we need all these." It becomes
bogged down. Yeah, so definitely, yeah.
That would really help to
discard all the things that are not
helpful for the concrete project.
Yeah, that sounds like a good approach.
Yeah. And exactly, the Rational Unified
Process is even worse in this situation
because
it is artifact driven by its design. So,
as you said, you usually end up with
projects who just do any kind of
documentation
architecture artifacts and whatever, but
have no time left to to actually
program.
So,
to to address this, one of
the the process experts I like very
much, Alistair Cockburn,
defined or used another way for his
Crystal Process family. So, he he
defines a family of development
processes, and you you just look at your
project. Um, you have some guidelines
like project size or uh criticality for
for life critical projects are different
from e-commerce projects or whatever.
Uh, and afterwards pick one of the
processes out of his family process
family, crystal process family,
um, that fits best so you don't have to
start at um, yeah, zero base like
Russian Unified Process where you
process where you have everything in
there. Uh, you have a um,
closer starting point to your actual
project, which is nice idea, I think.
Well, um, given these um, formalized
approaches to developing software,
I often heard and read about the opinion
that
software development should become more
and more repeatable, sort of controlled,
everyone knows what they are doing and
if you spend enough effort in to set up
your process, to train the people, you
will be able to
uh, predict with a high accuracy um,
when the project will be finished, how
many bugs there will be left, and well,
it's there's this keyword of
industrialization of software
development. What do you think about
that?
Yeah.
Uh,
very very important thing. I don't think
it works at all. It's the wrong metaphor
and we have to dive a bit deeper into
process theory as said in the beginning.
Um, if you look at process theory, there
are two kinds of processes, actually.
There are defined processes and and
empiric processes.
Uh, the defined processes are actually
repeatable. So, they basically say you
have the same input, use the same
process, and you will get the same
output. This is it's a bit like assembly
line thinking. You get what I mean? Um,
the the process actually defines the
working product.
Now, when you know when you when you're
speaking about processes, you mean the
abstract concept of a process. It's not
necessarily software, but just some
input, some processing, some output,
right?
Um some some development process. I
mean, you you you use for example the
the RUP again. Um you just give the same
input and you use the same development
process, RUP for example, and you will
get the defined same output as you said
in your in your question.
Well, but but but but
but that never happens for software.
Exactly.
No two No two development teams would
come up with the same design, for
Exactly. And And that is the the huge
misconception. Development Software
development is not a defined process.
Software development is an empiric
process, which is well, not the
opposite, but the other kind of
processes you have. And empiric
processes are actually for more complex
stuff, where you have feedback loops,
and where actually the process is not
the the only or the the defining key
variable in producing the output. I
mean, you think of designs, think of
product development, whatever. You have
always processes where people are
important, where creativity is
important, where communication is
important, and random things are
actually I mean,
every software developer knows he you
can't produce the same code twice
day after day. Just You have different
influences all over the day, so
it looks different every time you do it.
So, empiric That's an empiric process,
and that's why the industrialization and
assembly line metaphor doesn't work. The
it Assembly lines work for defined
processes, not for empiric processes,
actually.
But then, what about um
these um formalization things
um like CMM or ISO
series of standardization. I mean, the
higher CMM levels for example, they
sort of try to achieve um
repeatability. What do you think of
them?
Um same here. I I guess we we should do
a whole episode on CMMI actually because
it's a very complex thing and there um
you have this continuous model and this
uh stage model. So, um a lot to say
about that, but
basically, uh I don't think the idea
works. Um
a lot of things CMMI defines are great.
They are best practices in there. You
should do every every good project
actually should do the things or a lot
of things CMMI defines, but the idea
that just when you do this, you get good
software or you get uh software fast
enough or repeatable or with lesser bugs
or whatever is wrong because you can
get just get a bunch of idiots and let
them do CMMI 5 and you won't get any
software out. So, um the idea of repe-
repeatable software development just
through process or yeah, process quality
assurance is actually wrong. It just
works for defined processes and not for
empiric. So, uh it's a bit complicated
the CMMI things. You see, I mean, the
the techniques are actually good, but
the philos- philosophy is not so good or
it's wrong actually in my opinion.
Mhm.
Okay, well, from all of this, um I get
the impression that you don't really
like this metaphor of software
development as an assembly line.
Is that right?
Yeah, absolutely. It's it's the the
completely wrong metaphor in my opinion
and it's actually it's dangerous because
you get the idea of repeatability and
people don't matter and qualification
doesn't matter and creativity doesn't
matter and communication, whatever. All
the things that in at least in my
opinion are the the key factors, the
most important factors
are not important in this metaphor. So,
it's it's really dangerous and
it's not I mean look at car
manufacturers for example. There is also
a defined and an empiric process in
building cars. The defined process are
the ones where the cars are assembled in
in on the assembly line actually. So,
these are defined and repeatable
processes and it's not so important who
what people do these things. It's just
you can
do the quality assurance on the process
and your product gets
fine at least. So,
and then you have the
part front up where the car is actually
designed, where someone thinks about how
the car looks like, what what are the
engines,
where is the engine, all this this
development stuff. And this
kind of processes running there at
development of the car are actually
empiric processes again, like software
development. And if you look at these
parts in in every branch at least I
know,
the people work different. They don't
assure the quality by
quality assurance of the process. They
do increments, they get feedbacks from
customers and it's they do prototypes, a
lot of prototyping work. So, empiric
processes are different from defined
processes and
I think you have to to really understand
this issue before you get into software
development process. Otherwise, you get
out with some
of your process that don't work simply.
Mhm.
Okay, well,
this sounds like creative work has
empiric processes
and software development is sort of
much has has many aspects that require
creative work, creativity.
Yeah.
But then
if creativity is so central, so
important for software development,
um where do you see the limitations of
software process definitions if
creativity is in the foreground and the
key thing in creative work is to provide
an atmosphere of
um freedom where people freely think
creatively and sort of have the room to
evolve their ideas. How do these two
interact and how
how much freedom is necessary inside a
software development process?
Yeah.
Um
difficult to answer actually.
Yes, I think you have to um give the
people who do software development
freedom to to bring in their creativity,
their intelligence, their experience
actually. I mean, it doesn't make much
sense to get some highly paid software
developments with years of um experience
and afterwards just let them code down
four loops anyone or other guy has
defined. So,
um
use the or free the creativity of the
people and free the intelligence of the
people. Nevertheless, if your team grows
larger, uh
you you will end up with a mess when
everybody can do everything without a at
least defined way how to communicate and
when to communicate. I mean, um then you
have really everybody has to talk to
everybody before doing anything and and
uh communication costs grow
exponentially and that's a huge problem.
So, you it's it's like balancing out the
the two
factors. So, and that's one of the
points why all the the
we talked about fitting processes to to
uh actually projects. The team size and
all these things are influential factors
to get the right process and to to
customize your process. You it's always
a balancing act and someone has to do it
in front up or while the project. I
mean, you can also do some kind of meta
software development process where you
correct your software development
process every iteration or something
like that. So it It doesn't have to be
front up, of course.
Actually, much of what you're saying now
reminds me of the Agile Manifesto that
Yutta Eckstein mentioned in her
interview about Agile software
development. Sort of like um have the
minimum of minimum formalism that is
necessary to keep things going, but no
more than this minimum. Would you say
that every
software development process should be
Agile?
The question is
it's tricky question, actually.
First of all, Agile is
not so well defined in my opinion. I
mean, we have the Agile Manifesto which
doesn't say so much about actually
actual processes. So,
what is Agile and what is not Agile is
sometimes more a marketing thing than
anything else. So,
but yes, I would say
any process or yeah, process developer,
process designer should look into Agile
process because there is a lot of truth
and a lot of experience in there.
If your end product is
Agile process or not maybe may lie lay
in the eye of the beholder, but
it's
well, it's a difficult question, you you
see?
Yeah, I see that. I mean, sure Agile is
not really hard and well defined, but
I'm Agile develop Agile is about a value
system.
Yeah.
And do you Would you say that this value
system Yeah, these ideas I mean, no
matter whether you want to call it agile
or not. I mean, there are political
reasons, all kinds of reasons whether to
call it agile or not. But, um letting us
putting aside these political issues,
would you say that every process should
or could
um
be agile? Is that something to aim for
or do you see same limitations where
these agile values are not applicable?
I don't see any limitations for the
values, actually. I see limitations for
the
for the processes some people did. I
mean, I wouldn't do extreme programming
for any kind of project, but this is a
comment I would say for any any pro
process out there. So, it's not
something against extreme programming,
actually. But, the values you said and
the
You mean, you wouldn't do it for every
project.
Yeah, exactly. Um
the values in there to to focus on the
people, to focus on communication, to
um
don't overvalue the process at all um
are absolutely true. I think they they
should be valued actually by any develop
or development process designer, yes.
Okay, so basically the process is not
something to be cultivated for its own
end means, but it's um it's as a means
to an end to get things going. And so,
it should be as lean as possible.
Um and to get out of the way as much as
possible to just should define the
minimum of of structure that is needed.
Yeah, but that's that's of course a
difficult thing for the the actual
project manager afterwards. I mean, you
you have to find a balance again between
um not get letting the process get in
your way. On the other hand, if you just
get it out of the way every time, it
it's um
you will end up with a team that doesn't
follow the approach process anywhere.
So, it's it's really a difficult thing
for a project manager to to balance this
out, but the value is absolutely true
there.
Okay.
Well, another thing that you mentioned
is increments, incremental software
development.
How do you How important do you think
that is?
Absolutely important. I mean,
um
I don't think waterfall processes work
for any non-trivial project. Waterfall
basically meaning you you gather all the
requirements, then do all the design or
architecture work, then do all the
coding, and afterwards just test it and
release it. So, uh that doesn't work any
on for anything um more complex than
Hello World. So, um in to develop
incremental and iterative is absolutely
essential. And this is also the the huge
difference between the defined and
empiric processes. You always have find
some kind of increments in empiric
processes. Some call them prototypes in
other industries or um customer servers
or or whatever. Uh they are quite
different in different branches, but the
the notion is there everywhere where you
have
empiric processes. So, yes, it's
absolutely essential.
One thing that I've always been
wondering, people speak of incremental
and iterative development processes.
What is the difference between these?
Okay.
I I also
uh searched a lot for this because
Different people have different notions
on this, actually. Um
Some say iterations are the time boxes
and increments are the the release steps
where you add functionality. But, there
are also other um interpretations of the
these two words out there. So, I'm not
sure if there is an
real hard definition for it or is it if
it's just some yeah, soft or or
misinterpreted thing. I don't know
actually.
Okay, but now you mentioned both
increments in the requirements and also
time boxes. Maybe we should explain a
little about what iterative incremental
software development actually is what
it's all about.
Yeah.
Um idea is actually to to get feedback
as soon as possible and you have other
benefits too, but the the main idea is
you develop a part of your software,
release it to whatever a best case of
course customer because he can give you
the most
definitive feedback on your software.
So,
get the feedback and then in the next
increment or iteration, whatever,
develop the next part.
You have already feedback for the
customer. You don't do any unnecessary
work before. I mean I mean the the
other way to do it is you gather all the
requirements front up and do all the
architecture work front up, but you you
you just can't get feedback in this
process from your running software.
Customers always react on your
prototypes, on your iteration results
and they learn with you together. So,
it's hard to do to really do front up
design. It's it's nearly impossible
complex things because everybody learns.
You learn as a software developer and
the customer also learns and you you
incorporate this feedback in yeah, time
boxes or in iterations.
And
therefore you try to minimize anything
any unnecessary work.
Mhm.
And that's how you get to your full
product, of course, because increment
after increment,
um you you release more software until
the customer is actually happy and says,
"Okay, that's it. Fine, I can work with
this software."
So, if you sort of gather all the
requirements up front and then define
milestones in between, um and have a
master plan that is signed off before
the coding has begun, which features go
to which milestone would not be inter-
incremental software development.
Um
also controversial point. I mean, the
first times I heard about RUP, uh
Rational Unified Process, um it looked a
very much like what you you told me
right now. I mean, uh they had these
milestone notions and stuff like that.
Uh they became more iteration-focused
afterwards, at at least in my notion.
Um
I would say, if you can correct anytime
in your project, your your course, um
you might be on the right side. So, uh
if you use your first milestone to get
feedback and change your direction, it's
okay.
So, feedback and incorporating the
feedback and the experience is the key
thing.
And the more flexible you are up front,
the less
it costs to incorporate feedback later.
Mhm.
Actually, that's that's
I guess that's where the the the the
word agile comes from, to to react, to
be agile, and react on feedback, on on
changing um environments, whatever.
I mean, if you really worked on a on a
huge project, I mean, you know,
actually, the the world doesn't stop
while you do do software development.
And if you're
uh do
24-month project, actually, it looks a
lot different than when you start. So,
you have to change your course
usually on on huge projects. It's you
have no way out around it.
Mhm.
How long would you suggest to make your
increments?
Let's say with the iterations here
because I speak let's definitively speak
on the the time boxes when to do
integration and get it out to the
customer for for feedback.
A lot of this discussion actually out
there to right now
because many of the Agile people think
one or two weeks is
best fitting idea.
My experience it might be a bit short
especially one week. So in the project I
actually work right now on we will use
four weeks
four week iterations which work pretty
good and we will change it to two weeks
iterations as we get closer to the end
of development to get more feedback
because we can incorporate more
customers and and get more things out of
them. So
um
four weeks is okay. Some process
actually say up to eight weeks which is
a bit long in my opinion.
Okay, so anywhere from one to maybe
eight weeks, but anyway a couple of
weeks and not speaking of not counting
in months or let's say half a year
something like that.
Exactly and one week is actually for the
the pretty hardcore extreme programmers.
It's it's very short one week.
But it works.
How much effort should one put into the
upfront activities before you actually
start your
first iteration?
Mhm.
Um
I would I would answer I can't answer
this question.
And the point is um
it depends so much on on different
things. For example, if you do a project
in a field you you've done many projects
before, which basically means you know
the architecture of the thing, you know
the
technologies you use, and um
all these
things are pretty clear to you. Um you
can jump right into development without
any front up work, which is pretty
extreme actually, but it can work.
Actually, I've done this and it worked
very well.
but but you need to spend some time
gathering requirements.
Um
yes and no. I When I As I said, I did
this once and um I used extreme
programming actually on this project, uh
which me- means you have your on-site
customer,
and uh you do it on the fly more or
less. So, yes, you you have to find some
basic stories and talk about it, and of
course you have some some well, phase
front up where you you do the all the
the business stuff. You you have to
define how many people are on the
project, and you talk about the project
and the contents and requirements there,
too. So, it's not really fair to say
start on day zero. So, uh with coding.
Um but nevertheless, it's it's almost
without any um front up work. So,
Mhm.
but um there are other projects out
there, too.
Yeah, obviously for some if if the
domain is new, you need to spend some
time
Exactly.
Domain is new, techn- technology maybe a
huge step. I mean, if you do your first
.NET or Java or whatever thing, and uh
you have to do some serious research
before you um actually plan your project
and who you need and how to do it and
whatever. So, um
it depends
very very much on
um how unknown the the territory is of
the project you do.
Mhm.
And this this might lead to
some months of work. I would say if you
have more than two or three months front
up work, you are in trouble, too.
Somehow. I mean, either you have the
wrong experts on your project or
whatever.
But but it's an it's a smell,
I would say. So,
Mhm.
might be good, but unusually it's some
kind of problem.
Mhm.
Okay, then
you suggested rather short iterations,
couple of weeks.
Um and have a some sort of release at
the end of each iteration. I mean,
making some finishing some software to
be able to hand it off as a release
requires additional effort like testing,
like
creating install scripts and that sort
of thing. Um how much overhead or what
what part of the the time in your
experience does one spend on these
overhead activities as opposed to the
actual development?
Um
tricky answer.
it
if you do it like the way I describe, if
you release very very often and very
very often means from for example, once
a month or once a week even.
Um
it goes other way around. You your whole
team minimizes the effort to do these
integrations. They automate all the
scripts uh necessary for installation
and stuff like that. So, it it gets less
and less effort. And this is actually
good because integration is a huge huge
danger in a in a larger project because
you you shift all the work to the end of
your whatever to to your first milestone
or whatever your first release might be.
And usually projects break at these
points because then it's so much that's
not done and we do it at the first my my
stone release
that you you have no way to do actually
do it in in very reasonable time. So, I
would say it's it's a bit different. If
you would do it the normal way every
iteration you would have a problem
because it's too much work, too much
overhead. But you do all your design
decision decisions and all your build
scripts and all your stuff you need for
this
will be optimized for
frequent releases. And if you do
something like extreme programming where
you have your onsite customer who
actually tests all the day
that's not his main business but he he
will actually do it.
You have
integration anytime in your project. So,
work to be runnable as
often as
yeah, as often as possible actually.
Mhm.
But still even if you automate the
actual integration and the the
installation things, there's still
testing to be done. If you at least for
for normal release that should go out to
the customers. What level of quality
would you suggest you try to achieve if
you make this sort of frequent releases?
Okay, the religious answer would be
release quality anytime in your project
because everything else will get you but
you are near
at the end of the project. So,
this would be the the
answer from the book.
My life doesn't is easy actually.
Well,
you have to find a compromise there.
In in my project
For for for for for for big projects you
you can spend
I've seen weeks or even months spent in
testing after development was finished
to achieve to ensure high quality. You
can't do that if you release every
second week.
Yeah. To to give you an idea, I work on
a 50 person project right now something
about 50 and a little bit more.
And we have 10 testers all the time
doing tests, integration tests, and
well, iteration end tests, something
like that. We call it a bit different,
but nevertheless,
we they work all the day just for this.
So, it's it's 20% of the effort of the
project effort in testing all over the
time.
Mhm. And how much time do they get
for a let's say programming freeze to
ensure the quality
for a release?
We
these these 10 people do one week a
month. So,
one week a month, 10 persons for
these iteration end tests. And the
developers fix a bit of the stuff they
they actually find, but most of this
will be shifted into the normal normal
iteration planning stuff.
So, actually development stops one week
before this
this iteration release?
No, we we do it
different. We we stop at the
yeah, iteration release is okay.
Iteration end we we have iteration end.
So, developers stop to work on the
iteration,
and we in parallel begin iteration
planning of the next iteration and these
iteration tests actually. So, they run
parallel and for just about one week,
something like that, and then everything
yeah, starts again.
Mhm.
Okay.
But also,
this is the the project I work on is
very complicated, technical, very
complicated project. You might get away
with much less effort if your project is
simpler or more standard in some kind of
way. So,
as always, all the numbers I I I
depends heavily on your project. So,
don't take the numbers and simply use it
for as a benchmark or something for your
project.
Mhm.
Yeah.
Well, I guess that the actual
development processes that are out there
in the literature going to more detail
on this and you probably should choose
the process that actually fits your
requirements for complexity, for size,
for whatever.
Um so, what
are the some starting points? What are
the most frequently used processes, the
most or well, the ones that are most
worthy of
being start starting points for for
reading things up?
different uh
hierarchies
Um I
the most used I would say are customized
broads processes. At least in in my
experience, almost anytime I get in a
into a company, they don't use some
off-the-shelf process.
Um some better should, but nevertheless,
they have some
customized process.
Um so, uh I I have no idea actually if
there are more extreme programmers or
Rational Unified Process people out
there. I guess RUP is uh huge because a
lot of huge companies actually use it.
Um CMMI is not a process, so I wouldn't
count it in here.
Mhm.
Um okay. Uh for what you have or should
look into, depends on your project size.
I think you should look at least in in
the one of the
um well,
classic processes, something like your
Rational Unified Process process. Uh
or if you work for for some
um
yeah, for for some public service
things, you they they also have um rules
which process you have to use. In
Germany, for example, we have the
V-Model
um
for if you work for the government. So,
you you have to look into this, but also
take a look into the newer HR methods
because even if you don't end with using
one of them, extreme programming is good
to look at it in my opinion.
Um you should also look in
feature-driven development and Scrum,
which is not really a software
development process. Nevertheless, it's
it's very good. You should take a look
at it. And with a mixture of it, you
have a
pretty complete picture and build your
own process, I guess. Nevertheless,
process development or or customization
is a thing someone should do who has
experience with it. I wouldn't
really recommend it after reading just a
few books or without any prior software
development experience actually. I know
some people who define software
development processes and never really
did software development process.
Software development it's not a good
idea in my opinion. You have to
know how it feels.
Yeah, it's it's probably the same as
everywhere. If you start, just follow
the rules and once you get the
experience, you can break the rules, but
that's not where you should start.
So,
also one one comment. If you look at the
different processes, always take a look
who wrote the process. If you look at
something like extreme programming, I
would say it's a process a developer
wrote with all the the the pros and cons
of it. I mean it has
some advantages because it's very
development focused. It has also
disadvantages advantages because a lot
of things are missing.
Same for RUP where
Russian Unified Process almost ends when
it goes to software development. It does
everything but software development. So,
always keep in mind or try to to
understand who wrote this process. It's
it's it helps a lot.
So, let's say one of our listeners is a
software developer with some experience
and is about to embark on his or her
first
um let's say small-sized project
management role. Let's say five people,
half a year.
Um
any let's say some What would be your
short list of suggestions for her?
Um so
in kind of or the question was which
development processes or what kind of
Well, actually let's let's say someone
starts tomorrow.
Yeah.
Or let next week, let's say.
Okay.
And and what would you be your short
list of advice for this person?
Okay.
First of all,
um get the extreme programming book.
It's It's full Extreme Programming has
some huge advantage to me.
It's a minimal process software
development process in some
respect. I mean, you you can't take away
a single
development technique out of Extreme
Programming without getting into
trouble. You have You can replace it
with with something huge or whatever,
but you can't take away anything. So,
it's it's kind of the core of software
development processes.
Um the project you described pretty much
fits the hotspot of Extreme Programming.
So, I would say take a look at this one
as soon as you can do because there's
there are a lot of good advice
in there from unit testing to whatever.
Um
then listen to your team.
Always keep in mind the process is not
the thing that the people are the thing
that or are the the most important
factor success factor in your project.
So, especially if you have some people
who are very experienced, listen to
them. Use their experience.
These were would be the I guess the two
most
important ideas I I would give them.
Okay, great.
Then
I suggest I summarize what we covered
here.
Mhm.
I think the first key point is that
every team, every software development
project needs to have a software
development process. I mean,
either they have a documented one they
follow or they have
some sort of culture and things that are
done, but it's not documented. It's
implicit and implicit is usually worse
than explicit in this regard.
Mhm.
Um then we we saw that there is a lot of
a huge variety of different processes
out there
and they are they fit different kinds of
projects with regard to size, with
regard to
time, with regard to complexity in lots
of different ways.
So,
you you should get an overview in the
long run anyway and then
pick the one that fits your needs best
and customize it. If you have the
experience, customize it to to your
needs, to your project.
And
well, then finally, um
don't overrate the formalistic aspect.
Um keep in mind that um you have you're
dealing with an empirical process rather
than a defined process.
So, don't go for
absolute complete control because
software development is
creative work. It is not repeatable
in the sense that a production line is
repeatable.
That would be my my assessment of the
things we covered here.
Yeah, nice.
to add anything?
No, pretty complete. Good
good summary.
Okay, so we we covered the basic aspects
of software development processes in
this episode.
Um, it's a area. Give feedback, make
suggestions for things you'd like us to
look going to more detail about
and we'll go into different processes
and different topics in future episodes.
That's about it. Thanks for listening
and goodbye.
This was another episode of Software
Engineering Radio.
The Software Engineering Radio team
wants to thank Henning Pauly for
providing the music, as well as
lipsin.com for hosting and bandwidth.
For more information on the podcast,
past episodes, and feedback, go to
se-radio.net.